<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % poky SYSTEM "../poky.ent"> %poky; ] >

<chapter id='overview-manual-intro'>

<title>Getting Started with Yocto Project Manual</title>
    <section id='getting-started-welcome'>
        <title>Welcome</title>

        <para>
            Welcome to the Getting Started With Yocto Project Manual!
            This manual introduces the Yocto Project by providing concepts,
            software overviews, best-known-methods (BKMs), and any other
            high-level introductory information suitable for a new Yocto
            Project user.
        </para>

        <para>
            The following list describes what you can get from this manual:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Major Topic:</emphasis>
                    Provide a high-level description of this major topic.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Major Topic:</emphasis>
                    Provide a high-level description of this major topic.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Major Topic:</emphasis>
                    Provide a high-level description of this major topic.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Major Topic:</emphasis>
                    Provide a high-level description of this major topic.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            This manual does not give you the following:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Step-by-step Instructions for Development Tasks:</emphasis>
                    Instructional procedures reside in other manuals within
                    the Yocto Project documentation set.
                    For example, the
                    <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;'>Yocto Project Development Tasks Manual</ulink>
                    provides examples on how to perform various development
                    tasks.
                    As another example, the
                    <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_SDK_URL;'>Yocto Project Application Development and the Extensible Software Development Kit (eSDK)</ulink>
                    manual contains detailed instructions on how to install an
                    SDK, which is used to develop applications for target
                    hardware.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Reference Material:</emphasis>
                    This type of material resides in an appropriate reference
                    manual.
                    For example, system variables are documented in the
                    <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;'>Yocto Project Reference Manual</ulink>.
                    As another example, the
                    <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_BSP_URL;'>Yocto Project Board Support Package (BSP) Developer's Guide</ulink>
                    contains reference information on BSPs.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    <emphasis>Detailed Public Information Not Specific to the
                    Yocto Project:</emphasis>
                    For example, exhaustive information on how to use the
                    Source Control Manager Git is better covered with Internet
                    searches and official Git Documentation than through the
                    Yocto Project documentation.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='getting-started-overview-other-information'>
        <title>Other Information</title>

        <para>
            Because this manual presents information for many different
            topics, supplemental information is recommended for full
            comprehension.
            For additional introductory information on the Yocto Project, see
            the <ulink url='&YOCTO_HOME_URL;'>Yocto Project Website</ulink>.
            You can find an introductory to using the Yocto Project by working
            through the
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_QS_URL;'>Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink>.
        </para>

        <para>
            For a comprehensive list of links and other documentation, see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#resources-links-and-related-documentation'>Links and Related Documentation</ulink>"
            section in the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
