<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % poky SYSTEM "../poky.ent"> %poky; ] >

<article id='intro'>
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Yocto Project Quick Start</title>

        <copyright>
            <year>&COPYRIGHT_YEAR;</year>
            <holder>Linux Foundation</holder>
        </copyright>

        <legalnotice>
            <para>
                Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under
                the terms of the <ulink type="http" url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/uk/">Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 2.0 UK: England &amp; Wales</ulink> as published by Creative Commons.
            </para>
            <note>
                For the latest version of this manual associated with this
                Yocto Project release, see the
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_QS_URL;'>Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink>
                from the Yocto Project website.
            </note>
        </legalnotice>


        <abstract>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/yocto-project-transp.png"
                        width="6in" depth="1in"
                        align="right" scale="25" />
        </abstract>
    </articleinfo>

<section id='welcome'>
    <title>Welcome!</title>
    <para>
        Welcome to the Yocto Project!
        The Yocto Project is an open-source collaboration project focused on
        embedded Linux developers.
        Among other things, the Yocto Project uses a build system based on the
        OpenEmbedded (OE) project, which uses the
        <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#bitbake-term'>BitBake</ulink>
        tool, to construct complete Linux images.
        The BitBake and OE components are combined together to form
        <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#poky'>Poky</ulink>,
        a reference build system.
    </para>

    <para>
        If you don't have a system that runs Linux and you want to give the Yocto Project a test run,
        you might consider using the Yocto Project Build Appliance.
        The Build Appliance allows you to build and boot a custom embedded Linux image with the Yocto
        Project using a non-Linux development system.
        See the <ulink url='https://www.yoctoproject.org/tools-resources/projects/build-appliance'>Yocto
        Project Build Appliance</ulink> for more information.
    </para>

    <para>
        On the other hand, if you know all about open-source development, Linux development environments,
        Git source repositories and the like and you just want some quick information that lets you try out
        the Yocto Project on your Linux system, skip right to the
        "<link linkend='super-user'>Super User</link>" section at the end of this quick start.
    </para>

    <para>
        For the rest of you, this short document will give you some basic information about the environment and
        let you experience it in its simplest form.
        After reading this document, you will have a basic understanding of what the Yocto Project is
        and how to use some of its core components.
        This document steps you through a simple example showing you how to build a small image
        and run it using the Quick EMUlator (QEMU emulator).
    </para>

    <para>
        For more detailed information on the Yocto Project, you should check out these resources:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Website:</emphasis> The <ulink url='&YOCTO_HOME_URL;'>Yocto Project Website</ulink>
                provides the latest builds, breaking news, full development documentation, and a rich Yocto
                Project Development Community into which you can tap.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>FAQs:</emphasis> Lists commonly asked Yocto Project questions and answers.
                You can find two FAQs: <ulink url='&YOCTO_WIKI_URL;/wiki/FAQ'>Yocto Project FAQ</ulink> on
                a wiki, and the
                "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#faq'>FAQ</ulink>" chapter in
                the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Developer Screencast:</emphasis> The
                <ulink url='http://vimeo.com/36450321'>Getting Started with the Yocto Project - New Developer Screencast Tutorial</ulink>
                provides a 30-minute video created for users unfamiliar with
                the Yocto Project but familiar with Linux build systems.
                While this screencast is somewhat dated, the introductory
                and fundamental concepts are useful for the beginner.
                </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>

<section id='yp-intro'>
    <title>Introducing the Yocto Project Development Environment</title>
    <para>
        The Yocto Project through the OpenEmbedded build system provides an open source development
        environment targeting the ARM, MIPS, PowerPC and x86 architectures for a variety of
        platforms including x86-64 and emulated ones.
        You can use components from the Yocto Project to design, develop, build, debug, simulate,
        and test the complete software stack using Linux, the X Window System, GNOME Mobile-based
        application frameworks, and Qt frameworks.
    </para>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/yocto-environment.png"
                format="PNG" align='center' scalefit='1' width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <caption>
            <para>The Yocto Project Development Environment</para>
        </caption>
     </mediaobject>

    <para>
        Here are some highlights for the Yocto Project:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Provides a recent Linux kernel along with a set of system commands and libraries suitable for the embedded environment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Makes available system components such as X11, GTK+, Qt, Clutter, and SDL
            (among others) so you can create a rich user experience on devices
            that have display hardware.
            For devices that do not have a display or where you wish to use alternative UI
            frameworks, these components need not be installed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Creates a focused and stable core compatible with the OpenEmbedded
            project with which you can easily and reliably build and develop.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Fully supports a wide range of hardware and device emulation through the QEMU
            Emulator.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        The Yocto Project can generate images for many kinds of devices.
        However, the standard example machines target QEMU full-system emulation for x86, x86-64, ARM, MIPS,
        and PPC-based architectures as well as specific hardware such as the
        <trademark class='registered'>Intel</trademark> Desktop Board DH55TC.
        Because an image developed with the Yocto Project can boot inside a QEMU emulator, the
        development environment works nicely as a test platform for developing embedded software.
    </para>

    <para>
        Another important Yocto Project feature is the Sato reference User Interface.
        This optional GNOME mobile-based UI, which is intended for devices with
        restricted screen sizes, sits neatly on top of a device using the
        GNOME Mobile Stack and provides a well-defined user experience.
        Implemented in its own layer, it makes it clear to developers how they can implement
        their own user interface on top of a Linux image created with the Yocto Project.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='yp-resources'>
    <title>What You Need and How You Get It</title>

    <para>
        You need these things to develop projects in the Yocto Project
        environment:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            A host system with a minimum of 50 Gbytes of free disk space that
            is running a supported Linux distribution (i.e. recent releases
            of Fedora, openSUSE, CentOS, Debian, or Ubuntu).
            If the host system supports multiple cores and threads, you can
            configure the Yocto Project build system to significantly
            decrease the time needed to build images.
            </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            Appropriate packages installed on the system you are using for
            builds.
            </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            A release of the Yocto Project.
            </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id='the-linux-distro'>
        <title>The Linux Distribution</title>

        <para>
            The Yocto Project team is continually verifying more and more Linux
            distributions with each release.
            In general, if you have the current release minus one of the following
            distributions you should have no problems.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Ubuntu</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Fedora</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>openSUSE</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>CentOS</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Debian</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            For a more detailed list of distributions that support the Yocto Project,
            see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#detailed-supported-distros'>Supported Linux Distributions</ulink>" section
            in the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
            </para>
        <para>
            The OpenEmbedded build system should be able to run on any modern
            distribution that has the following versions for Git, tar, and
            Python.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Git 1.7.8 or greater</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>tar 1.24 or greater</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Python 2.7.3 or greater excluding Python
                   3.x, which is not supported.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Earlier releases of Python are known to not work and the
            system does not support Python 3 at this time.
            If your system does not meet any of these three listed
            version requirements, you can
            take steps to prepare the system so that you can still use the build
            system.
            See the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#required-git-tar-and-python-versions'>Required Git, tar, and Python Versions</ulink>"
            section in the Yocto Project Reference Manual for information.
        </para>
        <para>
            This document assumes you are running one of the previously noted
            distributions on your Linux-based host systems.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                If you attempt to use a distribution not in the above list,
                you may or may not have success.
                Yocto Project releases are tested against the stable Linux
                distributions listed in the
                "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#detailed-supported-distros'>Supported Linux Distributions</ulink>"
                section of the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
                If you encounter problems, please go to
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_BUGZILLA_URL;'>Yocto Project Bugzilla</ulink>
                and submit a bug.
                We are interested in hearing about your experience.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>

    <section id='packages'>
        <title>The Packages</title>

        <para>
            Packages and package installation vary depending on your development system
            and on your intent.
            For example, if you want to build an image that can run
            on QEMU in graphical mode (a minimal, basic build
            requirement), then the number of packages is different than if you want to
            build an image on a headless system or build out the Yocto Project
            documentation set.
            Collectively, the number of required packages is large
            if you want to be able to cover all cases.
            <note>In general, you need to have root access and then install the
                required packages.
                Thus, the commands in the following section may or may not work
                depending on whether or not your Linux distribution has
                <filename>sudo</filename> installed.</note>
        </para>

        <para>
            The next few sections list, by supported Linux Distributions, the required
            packages needed to build an image that runs on QEMU in graphical mode
            (e.g. essential plus graphics support).
        </para>

        <para>
            For lists of required packages for other scenarios, see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#required-packages-for-the-host-development-system'>Required Packages for the Host Development System</ulink>"
            section in the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
        </para>

        <section id='ubuntu'>
            <title>Ubuntu and Debian</title>

            <para>
                The essential and graphical support packages you need for a
                supported Ubuntu or Debian distribution are shown in the
                following command:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ sudo apt-get install &UBUNTU_HOST_PACKAGES_ESSENTIAL; libsdl1.2-dev xterm
                </literallayout>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='fedora'>
            <title>Fedora</title>

            <para>
                The essential and graphical packages you need for a supported
                Fedora distribution are shown in the following command:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ sudo yum install &FEDORA_HOST_PACKAGES_ESSENTIAL; SDL-devel xterm
                </literallayout>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='opensuse'>
            <title>OpenSUSE</title>

            <para>
                The essential and graphical packages you need for a supported
                OpenSUSE distribution are shown in the following command:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ sudo zypper install &OPENSUSE_HOST_PACKAGES_ESSENTIAL; libSDL-devel xterm
                </literallayout>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='centos'>
            <title>CentOS</title>

            <para>
                The essential and graphical packages you need for a supported
                CentOS distribution are shown in the following command:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ sudo yum install &CENTOS_HOST_PACKAGES_ESSENTIAL; SDL-devel xterm
                </literallayout>
                <note>Depending on the CentOS version you are using, other requirements
                    and dependencies might exist.
                    For details, you should look at the CentOS sections on the
                    <ulink url='https://wiki.yoctoproject.org/wiki/Poky/GettingStarted/Dependencies'>Poky/GettingStarted/Dependencies</ulink>
                    wiki page.</note>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id='releases'>
        <title>Yocto Project Release</title>

        <para>
            It is recommended that you get the latest Yocto Project files
            by setting up (cloning in
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#git'>Git</ulink> terms) a local
            copy of the
            <filename>poky</filename> Git repository on your host development
            system.
            Doing so allows you to contribute back to the Yocto Project project.
            For information on how to get set up using this method, see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#local-yp-release'>Yocto
            Project Release</ulink>" item in the Yocto Project Development Manual.
        </para>

        <para>
            You can also get the Yocto Project Files by downloading
            Yocto Project releases from the
            <ulink url="&YOCTO_HOME_URL;">Yocto Project website</ulink>.
            From the website, you just click "Downloads" in the navigation pane
            to the left to display all Yocto Project downloads.
            Current and archived releases are available for download.
            Nightly and developmental builds are also maintained at
            <ulink url="&YOCTO_AB_NIGHTLY_URL;"></ulink>.
            However, for this document a released version of Yocto Project is used.
        </para>

    </section>
</section>

<section id='test-run'>
    <title>A Quick Test Run</title>

    <para>
        Now that you have your system requirements in order, you can give the Yocto Project a try.
        This section presents some steps that let you do the following:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Build an image and run it in the QEMU emulator.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                Use a pre-built image and run it in the QEMU emulator.
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id='building-image'>
        <title>Building an Image</title>

        <para>
            In the development environment you will need to build an image whenever you change hardware
            support, add or change system libraries, or add or change services that have dependencies.
        </para>

        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/building-an-image.png" format="PNG" align='center' scalefit='1'/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
                <para>Building an Image</para>
            </caption>
         </mediaobject>

         <para>
             Use the following commands to build your image.
             The OpenEmbedded build process creates an entire Linux
             distribution, including the toolchain, from source.
             <note><title>Note about Network Proxies</title>
                 <para>
                     By default, the build process searches for source code
                     using a pre-determined order through a set of locations.
                     If you are working behind a firewall and your build system
                     is not set up for proxies, you could encounter problems
                     with the build process when fetching source code (e.g.
                     fetcher failures or Git failures).
                 </para>

                 <para>
                     If you do not know your proxy settings, consult your
                     local network infrastructure resources and get that
                     information.
                     A good starting point could also be to check your web
                     browser settings.
                     Finally, you can find more information on using the Yocto
                     Project behind a firewall in the Yocto Project Reference
                     Manual
                     <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#how-does-the-yocto-project-obtain-source-code-and-will-it-work-behind-my-firewall-or-proxy-server'>FAQ</ulink>
                     and on the
                     "<ulink url='https://wiki.yoctoproject.org/wiki/Working_Behind_a_Network_Proxy'>Working Behind a Network Proxy</ulink>"
                     wiki page.
                 </para>
             </note>
         </para>

         <para>
             <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ git clone &YOCTO_GIT_URL;/git/poky
     $ cd poky
     $ git checkout -b &DISTRO_NAME; origin/&DISTRO_NAME;
     $ source &OE_INIT_FILE;
             </literallayout>
         </para>

         <tip>
             <para>
                 To help conserve disk space during builds, you can add the
                 following statement to your project's configuration file,
                 which for this example is
                 <filename>poky/build/conf/local.conf</filename>.
                 Adding this statement deletes the work directory used for
                 building a package once the package is built.
                 <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     INHERIT += "rm_work"
                 </literallayout>
             </para>
         </tip>

         <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para>In the previous example, the first command uses
                 <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#git'>Git</ulink> to create
                 a local repository named <filename>poky</filename> that is a
                 clone of the upstream Yocto Project
                 <filename>poky</filename> repository.</para></listitem>
             <listitem><para>The third command checks out a local branch and
                 names it <filename>&DISTRO_NAME;</filename>.
                 The local branch tracks the upstream branch of the same name.
                 Creating your own branch based on the released branch ensures
                 you are using the latest files for that release.
                 </para></listitem>
             <listitem><para>
                 The final command runs the Yocto Project
                 <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#structure-core-script'><filename>&OE_INIT_FILE;</filename></ulink>
                 environment setup script.
                 Running this script defines OpenEmbedded build environment
                 settings needed to complete the build.
                 The script also creates the
                 <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#build-directory'>Build Directory</ulink>,
                 which is <filename>build</filename> in this case and is located
                 in the
                 <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#source-directory'>Source Directory</ulink>.
                 After the script runs, your current working directory is set
                 to the Build Directory.
                 Later, when the build completes, the Build Directory contains
                 all the files created during the build.
                 <note>
                     For information on running a memory-resident
                     <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#usingpoky-components-bitbake'>BitBake</ulink>,
                     see the
                     <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#structure-memres-core-script'><filename>oe-init-build-env-memres</filename></ulink>
                     setup script.
                 </note></para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para>
             Take some time to examine your <filename>local.conf</filename> file
             in your project's configuration directory, which is found in the Build Directory.
             The defaults in that file should work fine.
             However, there are some variables of interest at which you might look.
         </para>

         <para>
             By default, the target architecture for the build is <filename>qemux86</filename>,
             which produces an image that can be used in the QEMU emulator and is targeted at an
             <trademark class='registered'>Intel</trademark> 32-bit based architecture.
             To change this default, edit the value of the
             <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#var-MACHINE'><filename>MACHINE</filename></ulink>
             variable in the configuration file before launching the build.
         </para>

         <para>
             Another couple of variables of interest are the
             <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#var-BB_NUMBER_THREADS'><filename>BB_NUMBER_THREADS</filename></ulink> and the
             <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#var-PARALLEL_MAKE'><filename>PARALLEL_MAKE</filename></ulink> variables.
             By default, these variables are set to the number of processor
             cores your build host uses.
             However, if your build host uses multiple processor cores,
             you should increase these settings to twice the number of
             cores used.
             Doing so can significantly shorten your build time.
         </para>

        <para>
            Another consideration before you build is the package manager used when creating
            the image.
            By default, the OpenEmbedded build system uses the RPM package manager.
            You can control this configuration by using the
            <filename><ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#var-PACKAGE_CLASSES'><filename>PACKAGE_CLASSES</filename></ulink></filename> variable.
             For additional package manager selection information, see the
             "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#ref-classes-package'><filename>package*.bbclass</filename></ulink>"
             section in the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
        </para>

         <para>
             Continue with the following command to build an OS image for the target, which is
             <filename>core-image-sato</filename> in this example.
             For information on the <filename>-k</filename> option use the
             <filename>bitbake --help</filename> command, see the
             "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#usingpoky-components-bitbake'>BitBake</ulink>"
             section in the Yocto Project Reference Manual, or see the
             "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_BB_URL;#bitbake-user-manual-command'>BitBake Command</ulink>"
             section in the BitBake User Manual.
             <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ bitbake -k core-image-sato
             </literallayout>
             <note>
                 BitBake requires Python 2.6 or 2.7.  For more information on
                 this requirement, see the
                 "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#required-git-tar-and-python-versions'>Required Git, tar, and Python</ulink>"
                 section in the Yocto Project Reference Manual.
             </note>
             The final command runs the image using the QEMU emulator:
             <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ runqemu qemux86
             </literallayout>
             <note>
                 <para>
                     Depending on the number of processors and cores, the amount
                     of RAM, the speed of your Internet connection and other
                     factors, the build process could take several hours the
                     first time you run it.
                     Subsequent builds run much faster since parts of the build
                     are cached.
                 </para>
             </note>
         </para>
    </section>

    <section id='using-pre-built'>
        <title>Using Pre-Built Binaries and QEMU</title>

        <para>
            If hardware, libraries and services are stable, you can get started by using a pre-built binary
            of the filesystem image, kernel, and toolchain and run it using the QEMU emulator.
            This scenario is useful for developing application software.
        </para>

        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/using-a-pre-built-image.png" format="PNG" align='center' scalefit='1'/>
            </imageobject>
            <caption>
                <para>Using a Pre-Built Image</para>
            </caption>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>
            For this scenario, you need to do several things:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Install the appropriate stand-alone toolchain tarball.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Download the pre-built image that will boot with QEMU.
                You need to be sure to get the QEMU image that matches your target machine’s
                architecture (e.g. x86, ARM, etc.).</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Download the filesystem image for your target machine's architecture.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Set up the environment to emulate the hardware and then start the QEMU emulator.
                </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <section id='installing-the-toolchain'>
            <title>Installing the Toolchain</title>

            <para>
                You can download a tarball installer, which includes the
                pre-built toolchain, the <filename>runqemu</filename>
                script, and support files from the appropriate directory under
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_TOOLCHAIN_DL_URL;'></ulink>.
                Toolchains are available for 32-bit and 64-bit x86 development
                systems from the <filename>i686</filename> and
                <filename>x86_64</filename> directories, respectively.
                The toolchains the Yocto Project provides are based off the
                <filename>core-image-sato</filename> image and contain
                libraries appropriate for developing against that image.
                Each type of development system supports five or more target
                architectures.
            </para>

            <para>
                The names of the tarball installer scripts are such that a
                string representing the host system appears first in the
                filename and then is immediately followed by a string
                representing the target architecture.
            </para>

            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     poky-glibc-<replaceable>host_system</replaceable>-<replaceable>image_type</replaceable>-<replaceable>arch</replaceable>-toolchain-<replaceable>release_version</replaceable>.sh

     Where:
         <replaceable>host_system</replaceable> is a string representing your development system:

                    i686 or x86_64.

         <replaceable>image_type</replaceable> is a string representing the image you wish to
                develop a Software Development Toolkit (SDK) for use against.
                The Yocto Project builds toolchain installers using the
                following BitBake command:

                    bitbake core-image-sato -c populate_sdk

         <replaceable>arch</replaceable> is a string representing the tuned target architecture:

                    i586, x86_64, powerpc, mips, armv7a or armv5te

         <replaceable>release_version</replaceable> is a string representing the release number of the
                Yocto Project:

                    &DISTRO;, &DISTRO;+snapshot
            </literallayout>

            <para>
                For example, the following toolchain installer is for a 64-bit
                development host system and a i586-tuned target architecture
                based off the SDK for <filename>core-image-sato</filename>:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     poky-glibc-x86_64-core-image-sato-i586-toolchain-&DISTRO;.sh
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                Toolchains are self-contained and by default are installed into
                <filename>/opt/poky</filename>.
                However, when you run the toolchain installer, you can choose an
                installation directory.
            </para>

            <para>
                The following command shows how to run the installer given a toolchain tarball
                for a 64-bit x86 development host system and a 32-bit x86 target architecture.
                You must change the permissions on the toolchain
                installer script so that it is executable.
            </para>

            <para>
                The example assumes the toolchain installer is located in <filename>~/Downloads/</filename>.
                <note>
                    If you do not have write permissions for the directory into which you are installing
                    the toolchain, the toolchain installer notifies you and exits.
                    Be sure you have write permissions in the directory and run the installer again.
                </note>
            </para>

            <para>
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ ~/Downloads/poky-glibc-x86_64-core-image-sato-i586-toolchain-&DISTRO;.sh
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                For more information on how to install tarballs, see the
                "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_ADT_URL;#using-an-existing-toolchain-tarball'>Using a Cross-Toolchain Tarball</ulink>" and
                "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_ADT_URL;#using-the-toolchain-from-within-the-build-tree'>Using BitBake and the Build Directory</ulink>" sections in the Yocto Project Application Developer's Guide.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='downloading-the-pre-built-linux-kernel'>
            <title>Downloading the Pre-Built Linux Kernel</title>

            <para>
                You can download the pre-built Linux kernel suitable for running in the QEMU emulator from
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_QEMU_DL_URL;'></ulink>.
                Be sure to use the kernel that matches the architecture you want to simulate.
                Download areas exist for the five supported machine architectures:
                <filename>qemuarm</filename>, <filename>qemumips</filename>, <filename>qemuppc</filename>,
                <filename>qemux86</filename>, and <filename>qemux86-64</filename>.
            </para>

            <para>
                Most kernel files have one of the following forms:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     *zImage-qemu<replaceable>arch</replaceable>.bin
     vmlinux-qemu<replaceable>arch</replaceable>.bin

     Where:
         <replaceable>arch</replaceable> is a string representing the target architecture:
                x86, x86-64, ppc, mips, or arm.
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                You can learn more about downloading a Yocto Project kernel in the
                "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#local-kernel-files'>Yocto Project Kernel</ulink>"
                bulleted item in the Yocto Project Development Manual.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='downloading-the-filesystem'>
            <title>Downloading the Filesystem</title>

            <para>
                You can also download the filesystem image suitable for your target architecture from
                <ulink url='&YOCTO_QEMU_DL_URL;'></ulink>.
                Again, be sure to use the filesystem that matches the architecture you want
                to simulate.
            </para>

            <para>
                The filesystem image has two tarball forms: <filename>ext3</filename> and
                <filename>tar</filename>.
                You must use the <filename>ext3</filename> form when booting an image using the
                QEMU emulator.
                The <filename>tar</filename> form can be flattened out in your host development system
                and used for build purposes with the Yocto Project.
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     core-image-<replaceable>profile</replaceable>-qemu<replaceable>arch</replaceable>.ext3
     core-image-<replaceable>profile</replaceable>-qemu<replaceable>arch</replaceable>.tar.bz2

     Where:
         <replaceable>profile</replaceable> is the filesystem image's profile:
                   lsb, lsb-dev, lsb-sdk, lsb-qt3, minimal, minimal-dev, sato,
                   sato-dev, or sato-sdk. For information on these types of image
                   profiles, see the "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#ref-images'>Images</ulink>"
                   chapter in the Yocto Project Reference Manual.

         <replaceable>arch</replaceable> is a string representing the target architecture:
                x86, x86-64, ppc, mips, or arm.
                </literallayout>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='setting-up-the-environment-and-starting-the-qemu-emulator'>
            <title>Setting Up the Environment and Starting the QEMU Emulator</title>

            <para>
                Before you start the QEMU emulator, you need to set up the emulation environment.
                The following command form sets up the emulation environment.
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ source &YOCTO_ADTPATH_DIR;/environment-setup-<replaceable>arch</replaceable>-poky-linux-<replaceable>if</replaceable>

     Where:
         <replaceable>arch</replaceable> is a string representing the target architecture:
                i586, x86_64, ppc603e, mips, or armv5te.

         <replaceable>if</replaceable> is a string representing an embedded application binary interface.
              Not all setup scripts include this string.
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                Finally, this command form invokes the QEMU emulator
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ runqemu <replaceable>qemuarch</replaceable> <replaceable>kernel-image</replaceable> <replaceable>filesystem-image</replaceable>

     Where:
         <replaceable>qemuarch</replaceable> is a string representing the target architecture: qemux86, qemux86-64,
                    qemuppc, qemumips, or qemuarm.

         <replaceable>kernel-image</replaceable> is the architecture-specific kernel image.

         <replaceable>filesystem-image</replaceable> is the .ext3 filesystem image.

                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                Continuing with the example, the following two commands setup the emulation
                environment and launch QEMU.
                This example assumes the root filesystem (<filename>.ext3</filename> file) and
                the pre-built kernel image file both reside in your home directory.
                The kernel and filesystem are for a 32-bit target architecture.
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ cd $HOME
     $ source &YOCTO_ADTPATH_DIR;/environment-setup-i586-poky-linux
     $ runqemu qemux86 bzImage-qemux86.bin \
     core-image-sato-qemux86.ext3
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                The environment in which QEMU launches varies depending on the filesystem image and on the
                target architecture.
                For example, if you source the environment for the ARM target
                architecture and then boot the minimal QEMU image, the emulator comes up in a new
                shell in command-line mode.
                However, if you boot the SDK image, QEMU comes up with a GUI.
                <note>Booting the PPC image results in QEMU launching in the same shell in
                command-line mode.</note>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>

<section id='super-user'>
    <title>Super User
</title>

    <para>
        This section
        <footnote>
            <para>
                Kudos and thanks to Robert P. J. Day of
                <ulink url='http://www.crashcourse.ca'>CrashCourse</ulink> for providing the basis
                for this "expert" section with information from one of his
                <ulink url='http://www.crashcourse.ca/wiki/index.php/Yocto_Project_Quick_Start'>wiki</ulink>
                pages.
            </para>
        </footnote>
        gives you a minimal description of how to use the Yocto Project to build
        images for Beaglebone hardware starting from scratch.
        The steps were performed on a 64-bit Ubuntu 12.04 system that
        has four cores.
    </para>

    <section id='getting-yocto'>
        <title>Getting the Yocto Project</title>

        <para>
            Set up your
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#source-directory'>Source Directory</ulink>
            by using Git to clone the <filename>poky</filename>
            repository and then check out the release branch:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ cd ~
     $ git clone git://git.yoctoproject.org/poky
     $ cd poky
     $ git checkout -b &DISTRO_NAME; origin/&DISTRO_NAME;
            </literallayout>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='setting-up-your-host'>
        <title>Setting Up Your Host</title>

        <para>
            You need some packages for everything to work.
            Rather than duplicate them here, look at the
            "<link linkend='packages'>The Packages</link>"
            section earlier in this quick start.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='initializing-the-build-environment'>
        <title>Initializing the Build Environment</title>

        <para>
            From the root directory of your
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#source-directory'>Source Directory</ulink>,
            initialize your environment and provide a meaningful
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#build-directory'>Build Directory</ulink>
            name:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ source &OE_INIT_FILE; mybuilds
            </literallayout>
            At this point, the <filename>mybuilds</filename> directory has
            been created for you and it is now your current working directory.
            If you do not provide your own directory name,
            it defaults to <filename>build</filename>,
            which is inside the Source Directory.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='configuring-the-local.conf-file'>
        <title>Configuring the local.conf File</title>

        <para>
            Initializing the build environment creates a
            <filename>conf/local.conf</filename> configuration file
            in the Build Directory.
            You need to manually edit this file to specify the machine you
            are building and to optimize your build time.
            Here are the minimal changes to make:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     BB_NUMBER_THREADS = "8"
     PARALLEL_MAKE = "-j 8"
     MACHINE ?= "beaglebone"
            </literallayout>
            Briefly, set
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#var-BB_NUMBER_THREADS'><filename>BB_NUMBER_THREADS</filename></ulink>
            and
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_REF_URL;#var-PARALLEL_MAKE'><filename>PARALLEL_MAKE</filename></ulink> to
            twice your host processor's number of cores.
        </para>

        <para>
            A good deal that goes into a Yocto Project build is simply
            downloading all of the source tarballs.
            Steps exist that can help you be more efficient with gathering
            source files.
            For example, you can set up local mirrors that hold your
            source tarballs or you can pre-fetch all your source without
            initiating a build until later.
            For more information, see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#working-with-source-files'>Working with Source Files</ulink>"
            section in the Yocto Project Development Manual.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id='building-the-image'>
        <title>Building the Image</title>

        <para>
            At this point, you need to select an image to build for the
            Beaglebone hardware.
            If this is your first build using the Yocto Project, you should try
            the smallest and simplest image:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ bitbake core-image-minimal
            </literallayout>
            Now you just wait for the build to finish.
        </para>

        <para>
            By default, BitBake aborts when it encounters an error during
            the build.
            If you want to make sure the build continues even when BitBake
            encounters an error, use this variation:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ bitbake -k core-image-minimal
            </literallayout>
        </para>

        <para>
            Once you have your image, you can take steps to load and boot it on
            the target hardware.
        </para>

        <para>
            You can learn about BitBake in general by reading the
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_BB_URL;'>BitBake User Manual</ulink>.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>

</article>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
