<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % poky SYSTEM "../poky.ent"> %poky; ] >

<chapter id='toaster-manual-intro'>
<title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
        Toaster is an Application Programming Interface (API) and
        web-based interface to the OpenEmbedded build system, which uses
        BitBake.
        Both interfaces are based on a Representational State Transfer
        (REST) API that queries for and returns build information using
        <filename>GET</filename> and <filename>JSON</filename>.
        These types of search operations retrieve sets of objects from
        a datastore used to collect build information.
        The results contain all the data for the objects being returned.
        You can order the results of the search by key and the search
        parameters are consistent for all object types.
    </para>

    <para>
        You can use Toaster in several different modes:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Interactive Mode:</emphasis>
                In this mode, you can record builds and statistics.
                In Interactive Mode, you have direct access to the
                <filename>bitbake</filename> command, which you use to build
                images.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Managed Mode:</emphasis>
                In this mode, Toaster handles the build configuration GUI
                (through Project pages) and build scheduling and execution.
                Additionally, in addition to these features, builds are
                triggered through the web interface.
                You do not have direct access to the
                <filename>bitbake</filename> command.</para>

                <para>Managed Mode also works two separate ways: Local
                Managed Mode and Remote Managed Mode.
                Local Managed Mode is the out-of-box mode available once
                you checkout poky and allows you to perform builds on your
                local machine.
                Remote Managed Mode, also known as Hosted Toaster, is a
                production setup best for organizations supporting multiple
                users and for organizations using customized Toaster
                installations.
                </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        Using the interfaces you can do the following:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>See information about the tasks executed
                and reused during the build.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>See what is built (recipes and
                packages) and what packages were installed into the final
                image.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>See performance-related information such
                as build time, CPU usage, and disk I/O.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Examine error, warning and trace messages
                to aid in debugging.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <note>
        <para>
            This release of Toaster provides you with information
            about a BitBake run.
            The tool does not allow you to configure and launch a build.
            However, future development includes plans to integrate the
            configuration and build launching capabilities of
            <ulink url='&YOCTO_HOME_URL;/tools-resources/projects/hob'>Hob</ulink>.
        </para>

        <para>
            For more information on using Hob to build an image,
            see the
            "<ulink url='&YOCTO_DOCS_DEV_URL;#image-development-using-hob'>Image Development Using Hob</ulink>"
           section in the Yocto Project Development Manual.
        </para>
    </note>

    <para>
        The remainder of this manual describes what you need to have in
        place to use Toaster, how to start it, use it, and stop it.
        For additional information on installing and running Toaster, see the
        "<ulink url='https://wiki.yoctoproject.org/wiki/Toaster#Installation_and_Running'>Installation and Running</ulink>"
        section of the "Toaster" wiki page.
        For complete information on the API and its search operation
        URI, parameters, and responses, see the
        <ulink url='https://wiki.yoctoproject.org/wiki/REST_API_Contracts'>REST API Contracts</ulink>
        Wiki page.
    </para>
</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
