<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % poky SYSTEM "../poky.ent"> %poky; ] >

<chapter id='sdk-using-the-standard-sdk'>

<title>Using the Standard SDK</title>

<para>
    This chapter describes how to use a standard SDK.
    Information covers installing the SDK and task-based procedures common
    for developing with a standard SDK.
    <note>
        The tasks you can perform using a standard SDK are also applicable
        when you are using an extensible SDK.
        For information on the differences when using an extensible SDK as
        compared to an extensible SDK, see the
        "<link linkend='sdk-extensible'>Using the Extensible SDK</link>"
        chapter.
    </note>
</para>

<section id='sdk-setting-up-to-use-the-standard-sdk'>
    <title>Setting Up to Use the Standard SDK</title>

    <para>
        Here is a list of items I think need addressed in this section:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>What is your situation?</emphasis></para>
                <para>In other words, is the developer on a machine that
                has YP on it?
                Are they on a machine that does not?
                Is the image they are developing against available as a
                pre-built, down-loadable image and can they get it?</para>
                <para>Depending on the scenario, there are different ways
                to make sure the machine they are using is ready to use a
                standard SDK.
                I think we need to cover the various situations in this
                section.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>What are the recommendations?</emphasis></para>
                <para>What is the most common development scenario?
                Is there a recommended development flow we want to present
                when using a standard SDK?
                What conditions in a development scenario warrant use of
                just the standard SDK as compared to the extensible SDK?
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>What procedures do we want to cover to set up
                the standard SDK?</emphasis></para>
                <para>There is a ton of setup information in the
                current ADT manual regarding getting, building, and installing
                an SDK.
                We would ignore the stuff about the ADT installer script
                since I presume that is going away.
                But, there are steps to download and existing
                <filename>.sh</filename> install script, build out the
                toolchains assuming your system has YP on it and you can run
                BitBake, getting the root filesystem, getting an image so you
                run QEMU on your system, etc.
                </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>

<section id='sdk-using-the-sdk-to-task-1'>
    <title>Using the SDK to <replaceable>item 1</replaceable></title>

    <para>
        Describe the specific task you are going to accomplish with the SDK.
        Provide a diagram showing the rough flow of the task.
        Provide specific steps using a real example that works through the
        task.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='sdk-using-the-sdk-to-task-2'>
    <title>Using the SDK to <replaceable>item-2</replaceable></title>

    <para>
        Describe the specific task you are going to accomplish with the SDK.
        Provide a diagram showing the rough flow of the task.
        Provide specific steps using a real example that works through the
        task.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='sdk-using-the-sdk-to-task-3'>
    <title>Using the SDK to <replaceable>item-3</replaceable></title>

    <para>
        Describe the specific task you are going to accomplish with the SDK.
        Provide a diagram showing the rough flow of the task.
        Provide specific steps using a real example that works through the
        task.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='sdk-using-the-sdk-to-task-x'>
    <title>Using the SDK to <replaceable>item-x</replaceable></title>

    <para>
        Describe the specific task you are going to accomplish with the SDK.
        Provide a diagram showing the rough flow of the task.
        Provide specific steps using a real example that works through the
        task.
    </para>
</section>

</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
