<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="platdev">
<title>Platform Development with the Yocto Project</title>

    <section id="platdev-appdev">
    <title>Application Development Using the Yocto Project</title>
    <para>
        The Yocto Project supports several methods of application development through which 
        you can create user-space software designed to run on an embedded device that uses
        a Linux Yocto image developed with the Yocto Project. 
        This flexibility allows you to choose the method that works best for you.  
        This chapter describes each development method.
    </para>

        <section id="platdev-appdev-external-sdk">
        <title>External Development Using the Meta-Toolchain</title>
        <para>
            The Yocto Project provides toolchains that allow you to develop your application 
            outside of the Yocto Project build system for specific hardware.
            These toolchains (called meta-toolchains) contain cross-development tools such as compilers, 
            linkers, and debuggers that build your application for your target device.
            The Yocto Project also provides images that have toolchains for supported 
            architectures included within the image.
            This allows you to compile, debug, or profile applications directly on the target device.
            See  
            <xref linkend='ref-images'>Reference: Images</xref> for a listing of the image
            types that Yocto Project supports.
        </para> 
        <para>
            Using the BitBake tool you can build a meta-toolchain or meta-toolchain-sdk target,
            which generates a tarball. 
            Unpacking  this tarball into the <filename class="directory">/opt/poky</filename> directory 
            on your host produces a setup script 
            (e.g. <filename>/opt/poky/environment-setup-i586-poky-linux</filename>) that 
            you can <filename>source</filename> to initialize your build environment. 
            Sourcing this script adds the compiler, QEMU scripts, QEMU binary, a special version of 
            <filename>pkgconfig</filename> and other 
            useful utilities to the <filename>PATH</filename> variable used by the Yocto Project
            build environment. 
            Variables to assist <filename>pkgconfig</filename> and 
            Autotools are also defined so that, for example, <filename>configure</filename>
            can find pre-generated test results for tests that need target hardware on which to run.
        </para>
        <para>
            Using the toolchain with Autotool-enabled packages is straightforward - just pass the 
            appropriate <filename>host</filename> option to <filename>configure</filename>. 
            Following is an example:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ ./configure --host=arm-poky-linux-gnueabi
            </literallayout>
            For projects that are not Autotool-enabled, it is usually just a case of ensuring 
            you point to and use the cross-toolchain.
            For example, the following two lines of code in a <filename>Makefile</filename>
            that builds your application
            specify to use the cross-compiler <filename>arm-poky-linux-gnueabi-gcc</filename>
            and linker <filename>arm-poky-linux-gnueabi-ld</filename>, which are part of the 
            meta-toolchain you would have previously established:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     CC=arm-poky-linux-gnueabi-gcc;
     LD=arm-poky-linux-gnueabi-ld;
            </literallayout>
        </para>
        </section>

        <section id="using-the-eclipse-and-anjuta-plug-ins">
        <title>External Development Using the Eclipse Plug-in</title>
        <para>
            The current release of the Yocto Project supports the Eclipse IDE plug-in
            to make developing software easier for the application developer. 
            The plug-in provides capability extensions to the graphical IDE to allow
            for cross compilation, deployment and execution of the application within a QEMU 
            emulation session. 
            Support of the Eclipse plug-in also allows for cross debugging and
            profiling.  
            Additionally, the Eclipse plug-in provides a suite of tools 
            that allows the developer to perform remote profiling, tracing, collection of 
            power consumption data, collection of latency data and collection of performance data.
        </para>
        <note>
            The current release of the Yocto Project no longer supports the Anjuta plug-in.
            However, the Poky Anjuta Plug-in is available to download directly from the Poky 
            Git repository located through the web interface at
            <ulink url="http://git.yoctoproject.org/"></ulink> under IDE Plugins.
            The community is free to continue supporting it beyond the Yocto Project 0.9
            Release.            
        </note>
        <para>
            To use the Eclipse plug-in you need the Eclipse Framework (Helios 3.6.1) along 
            with other plug-ins installed into the Eclipse IDE.
            Once you have your environment setup you need to configure the Eclipse plug-in.
            For information on how to install and configure the Eclipse plug-in, see the
            <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/adt-manual/adt-manual.html#adt-eclipse'>
            "Working Within Eclipse"</ulink> chapter in the 
            <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/adt-manual/adt-manual.html'>
            "Application Development Toolkit (ADT) User's Guide."</ulink>
         </para>
         </section>

        <section id="platdev-appdev-qemu">
        <title>External Development Using the QEMU Emulator</title>
        <para>
            Running Poky QEMU images is covered in the 
            <ulink url="http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/yocto-quick-start/yocto-project-qs.html">
            Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink> in the "A Quick Test Run" section.
        </para>
        <para>
            The QEMU images shipped with the Yocto Project contain complete toolchains
            native to their target architectures.
            This support allows you to develop applications within QEMU similar to the way 
            you would using a normal host development system.
        </para>

        <para> 
            Speed can be an issue depending on the target and host architecture mix.
            For example, using the <filename>qemux86</filename> image in the emulator 
            on an Intel-based 32-bit (x86) host machine is fast because the target and 
            host architectures match.
            On the other hand, using the <filename>qemuarm</filename> image on the same Intel-based
            host can be slower.
            But, you still achieve faithful emulation of ARM-specific issues. 
        </para>

        <para>
            To speed things up, the QEMU images support using <filename>distcc</filename>
            to call a cross-compiler outside the emulated system. 
            If you used <filename>runqemu</filename> to start QEMU, and 
            <filename>distccd</filename> is present on the host system, any BitBake cross-compiling 
            toolchain available from the build system is automatically
            used from within QEMU simply by calling <filename>distcc</filename>.
            You can accomplish this by defining the cross-compiler variable 
            (e.g. <filename>export CC="distcc"</filename>).
            Alternatively, if a suitable SDK/toolchain is present in 
            <filename>/opt/poky</filename> the toolchain is also automatically used.
        </para>

        <para>
            Several mechanisms exist that let you connect to the system running on the 
            QEMU emulator:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>QEMU provides a framebuffer interface that makes standard 
                    consoles available.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Generally, headless embedded devices have a serial port.
                    If so, you can configure the operating system of the running image
                    to use that port to run a console. 
                    The connection uses standard IP networking.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>The QEMU images have a Dropbear secure shell (ssh) server 
                    that runs with the root password disabled.
                    This allows you to use standard <filename>ssh</filename> and 
                    <filename>scp</filename> commands.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>The QEMU images also contain an embedded Network Files
                    System (NFS) server that exports the image's root filesystem.
                    This allows you to make the filesystem available to the 
                    host.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        </section>              

        <section id="platdev-appdev-insitu">
        <title>Development Using Yocto Project Directly</title>
        <para>
            Working directly with the Yocto Project is a fast and effective development technique.
            The idea is that you can directly edit files in a working directory
            (<glossterm><link linkend='var-WORKDIR'>WORKDIR</link></glossterm>) 
            or the source directory (<glossterm><link linkend='var-S'>S</link></glossterm>) 
            and then force specific tasks to rerun in order to test the changes. 
            An example session working on the matchbox-desktop package might 
            look like this:
        </para>

        <para>
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ bitbake matchbox-desktop
     $ sh
     $ cd tmp/work/armv5te-poky-linux-gnueabi/matchbox-desktop-2.0+svnr1708-r0/
     $ cd matchbox-desktop-2
     $ vi src/main.c
           .
           .
      [Make your changes]
           .
           .
     $ exit
     $ bitbake matchbox-desktop -c compile -f
     $ bitbake matchbox-desktop
            </literallayout>
        </para>

        <para>
            This example builds the <filename>matchbox-desktop</filename> package, 
            creates a new terminal, changes into the work directory for the package,
            changes a file, exits out of the terminal, and then recompiles the 
            package. 
            Instead of using <filename>sh</filename>,
            you can also use two different terminals. 
            However, the risk of using two terminals is that a command like 
            <filename>unpack</filename> could destroy your changes in the
            work directory.  
            Consequently, you need to work carefully.
        </para>

        <para>
            It is useful when making changes directly to the work directory files to do
            so using the Quilt tool as detailed in the 
            <link linkend='usingpoky-modifying-packages-quilt'> 
            Modifying Package Source Code with Quilt</link> section. 
            Using Quilt, you can copy patches into the recipe directory and use the patches directly 
            through use of the <glossterm><link linkend='var-SRC_URI'>SRC_URI</link></glossterm> variable.
        </para>

        <para>
            For a review of the skills used in this section, see the 
            <link linkend="usingpoky-components-bitbake">BitBake</link> and 
            <link linkend="usingpoky-debugging-taskrunning">Running Specific Tasks</link> sections
            in this manual.
        </para>
        </section>

        <section id="platdev-appdev-devshell">
        <title>Development Within a Development Shell</title>

        <para>
            When debugging certain commands or even when just editing packages, 
            <filename>devshell</filename> can be a useful tool.
            Using <filename>devshell</filename> differs from the example shown in the previous 
            section in that when you invoke <filename>devshell</filename> source files are 
            extracted into your working directory and patches are applied. 
            Then, a new terminal is opened and you are placed in the working directory.
            In the new terminal all the Yocto Project build-related environment variables are 
            still defined so you can use commands such as <filename>configure</filename> and 
            <filename>make</filename>. 
            The commands execute just as if the Yocto Project build system were executing them. 
            Consequently, workng this way can be helpful when debugging a build or preparing 
            software to be used with the Yocto Project build system.
        </para>

        <para>
            Following is an example that uses <filename>devshell</filename> on a target named
            <filename>matchbox-desktop</filename>:
        </para>

        <para>
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ bitbake matchbox-desktop -c devshell
            </literallayout>
        </para>

        <para>
            This command opens a terminal with a shell prompt within the Poky 
            environment. 
            The following occurs:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>The <filename>PATH</filename> variable includes the 
                    cross-toolchain.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>The <filename>pkgconfig</filename> variables find the correct 
                    <filename>.pc</filename> files.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>The <filename>configure</filename> command finds the 
                    Yocto Project site files as well as any other necessary files.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Within this environment, you can run <filename>configure</filename>
            or <filename>compile</filename> commands as if they were being run by 
            the Yocto Project build system itself.
            As noted earlier, the working directory also automatically changes to the 
            source directory (<glossterm><link linkend='var-S'>S</link></glossterm>).
        </para>

        <para> 
            When you are finished, you just exit the shell or close the terminal window.
        </para>

        <para>
            The default shell used by <filename>devshell</filename> is xterm. 
            You can use other terminal forms by setting the 
            <glossterm><link linkend='var-TERMCMD'>TERMCMD</link></glossterm> and 
            <glossterm><link linkend='var-TERMCMDRUN'>TERMCMDRUN</link></glossterm> variables 
            in the Yocto Project's <filename>local.conf</filename> file found in the build
            directory. 
            For examples of the other options available, see the "UI/Interaction Configuration"
            section of the  
            <filename>meta/conf/bitbake.conf</filename> configuration file in the Yocto Project
            files. 
        </para>

        <para>
            Because an external shell is launched rather than opening directly into the 
            original terminal window, it allows easier interaction with Bitbake's multiple 
            threads as well as accomodates a future client/server split.
        </para>

        <note>
            <para>It is worth remembering that when using <filename>devshell</filename>
            you need to use the full compiler name such as <filename>arm-poky-linux-gnueabi-gcc</filename> 
            instead of just using <filename>gcc</filename>.
            The same applies to other applications such as <filename>binutils</filename>, 
            <filename>libtool</filename> and so forth.
            The Yocto Project has setup environment variables such as <filename>CC</filename>
            to assist applications, such as <filename>make</filename> to find the correct tools.</para>
            <para>It is also worth noting that <filename>devshell</filename> still works over
            X11 forwarding and similar situations</para>
        </note>
        </section>

        <section id="platdev-appdev-srcrev">
        <title>Development Within Yocto Project for a Package that Uses an External SCM</title>

        <para>
            If you're working on a recipe that pulls from an external Source Code Manager (SCM), it 
            is possible to have the Yocto Project build system notice new changes added to the 
            SCM and then build the package that depends on them using the latest version. 
            This only works for SCMs from which it is possible to get a sensible revision number for changes.
            Currently, you can do this with Apache Subversion (SVN), Git, and Bazaar (BZR) repositories.
        </para>

        <para>
            To enable this behavior, simply add the following to the <filename>local.conf</filename>
            configuration file in the build directory of the Yocto Project files:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     SRCREV_pn-&lt;PN&gt; = "${AUTOREV}"
            </literallayout>
            where <filename>PN</filename> 
            is the name of the package for which you want to enable automatic source 
            revision updating.
        </para>
        </section>
    </section>

<section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug">
    <title>Debugging With the GNU Project Debugger (GDB) Remotely</title>

    <para>
        GDB allows you to examine running programs, which in turn help you to understand and fix problems. 
        It also allows you to perform post-mortem style analysis of program crashes. 
        GDB is available as a package within the Yocto Project and by default is 
        installed in sdk images.
        See <xref linkend='ref-images'>Reference: Images</xref> for a description of these
        images. 
        You can find information on GDB at <ulink url="http://sourceware.org/gdb/"/>.
    </para>

    <tip>
        For best results, install <filename>-dbg</filename> packages for the applications 
        you are going to debug.
        Doing so makes available extra debug symbols that give you more meaningful output.
    </tip>

    <para>
        Sometimes, due to memory or disk space constraints, it is not possible
        to use GDB directly on the remote target to debug applications. 
        These constraints arise because GDB needs to load the debugging information and the 
        binaries of the process being debugged. 
        Additionally, GDB needs to perform many computations to locate information such as function 
        names, variable names and values, stack traces and so forth - even before starting the 
        debugging process. 
        These extra computations place more load on the target system and can alter the
        characteristics of the program being debugged.
    </para>

    <para>
        To help get past the previously mentioned constraints, you can use Gdbserver.
        Gdbserver runs on the remote target and does not load any debugging information 
        from the debugged process.
        Instead, a GDB instance processes the debugging information that is run on a 
        remote computer - the host GDB. 
        The host GDB then sends control commands to Gdbserver to make it stop or start the debugged 
        program, as well as read or write memory regions of that debugged program. 
        All the debugging information loaded and processed as well
        as all the heavy debugging is done by the host GDB.
        Offloading these processes gives the Gdbserver running on the target a chance to remain 
        small and fast.
    </para>

    <para>
        Because the host GDB is responsible for loading the debugging information and 
        for doing the necessary processing to make actual debugging happen, the 
        user has to make sure the host can access the unstripped binaries complete
        with their debugging information and also be sure the target is compiled with no optimizations. 
        The host GDB must also have local access to all the libraries used by the 
        debugged program. 
        Because Gdbserver does not need any local debugging information, the binaries on
        the remote target can remain stripped. 
        However, the binaries must also be compiled without optimization 
        so they match the host's binaries.
    </para>

    <para>
        To remain consistent with GDB documentation and terminology, the binary being debugged 
        on the remote target machine is referred to as the "inferior" binary.
        For documentation on GDB see the  
        <ulink url="http://sourceware.org/gdb/documentation/">GDB site</ulink>.
    </para>

    <section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdbserver">
        <title>Launching Gdbserver on the Target</title>

        <para>
            First, make sure Gdbserver is installed on the target. 
            If it is not, install the package <filename>gdbserver</filename>, which needs the 
            <filename>libthread-db1</filename> package.
        </para>

        <para>
            As an example, to launch Gdbserver on the target and make it ready to "debug" a 
            program located at <filename>/path/to/inferior</filename>, connect
            to the target and launch:
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ gdbserver localhost:2345 /path/to/inferior
            </literallayout>
            Gdbserver should now be listening on port 2345 for debugging
            commands coming from a remote GDB process that is running on the host computer.
            Communication between Gdbserver and the host GDB are done using TCP. 
            To use other communication protocols, please refer to the  
            <ulink url='http://www.gnu.org/software/gdb/'>Gdbserver documentation</ulink>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdb">
        <title>Launching GDB on the Host Computer</title>

        <para>
            Running GDB on the host computer takes a number of stages.
            This section describes those stages.
        </para>

        <section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdb-buildcross">
            <title>Building the Cross-GDB Package</title>
            <para>
                A suitable GDB cross-binary is required that runs on your host computer but
                also knows about the the ABI of the remote target. 
                You can get this binary from the the Yocto Project meta-toolchain.
                Here is an example:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'> 
     /usr/local/poky/eabi-glibc/arm/bin/arm-poky-linux-gnueabi-gdb
                </literallayout> 
                where <filename>arm</filename> is the target architecture and 
                <filename>linux-gnueabi</filename> the target ABI.
            </para>

            <para>
                Alternatively, the Yocto Project can build the <filename>gdb-cross</filename> binary. 
                Here is an example:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ bitbake gdb-cross
                </literallayout>
                Once the binary is built, you can find it here: 
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     tmp/sysroots/&lt;host-arch&gt;/usr/bin/&lt;target-abi&gt;-gdb 
                </literallayout>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdb-inferiorbins">
            <title>Making the Inferior Binaries Available</title>

            <para>
                The inferior binary (complete with all debugging symbols) as well as any
                libraries (and their debugging symbols) on which the inferior binary depends
                need to be available.
                There are a number of ways you can make these available.
            </para>

            <para>
                Perhaps the easiest way is to have an 'sdk' image that corresponds to the plain
                image installed on the device. 
                In the case of <filename>core-image-sato</filename>, 
                <filename>core-image-sdk</filename> would contain suitable symbols. 
                Because the sdk images already have the debugging symbols installed, it is just a 
                question of expanding the archive to some location and then informing GDB. 
            </para>

            <para>
                Alternatively, Yocto Project can build a custom directory of files for a specific 
                debugging purpose by reusing its <filename>tmp/rootfs</filename> directory.
                This directory contains the contents of the last built image. 
                This process assumes two things:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>The image running on the target was the last image to 
                    be built by the Yocto Project.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>The package (<filename>foo</filename> in the following 
                    example) that contains the inferior binary to be debugged has been built 
                    without optimization and has debugging information available.</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                The following steps show how to build the custom directory of files:
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem><para>Install the package (<filename>foo</filename> in this case) to 
                        <filename>tmp/rootfs</filename>:
                        <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ tmp/sysroots/i686-linux/usr/bin/opkg-cl -f \
     tmp/work/&lt;target-abi&gt;/core-image-sato-1.0-r0/temp/opkg.conf -o \
     tmp/rootfs/ update
                        </literallayout></para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Install the debugging information:
                        <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ tmp/sysroots/i686-linux/usr/bin/opkg-cl -f \
     tmp/work/&lt;target-abi&gt;/core-image-sato-1.0-r0/temp/opkg.conf \
     -o tmp/rootfs install foo

     $ tmp/sysroots/i686-linux/usr/bin/opkg-cl -f \
     tmp/work/&lt;target-abi&gt;/core-image-sato-1.0-r0/temp/opkg.conf \
     -o tmp/rootfs install foo-dbg
                        </literallayout></para></listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdb-launchhost">
            <title>Launch the Host GDB</title>

            <para>
                To launch the host GDB, you run the <filename>cross-gdb</filename> binary and provide 
                the inferior binary as part of the command line.  
                For example, the following command form continues with the example used in 
                the previous section.  
                This command form loads the <filename>foo</filename> binary
                as well as the debugging information:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ &lt;target-abi&gt;-gdb rootfs/usr/bin/foo
                </literallayout>
                Once the GDB prompt appears, you must instruct GDB to load all the libraries
                of the inferior binary from <filename>tmp/rootfs</filename> as follows:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ set solib-absolute-prefix /path/to/tmp/rootfs
                </literallayout>
                The pathname <filename>/path/to/tmp/rootfs</filename> must either be
                the absolute path to <filename>tmp/rootfs</filename> or the location at which 
                binaries with debugging information reside.
            </para>

            <para>
                At this point you can have GDB connect to the Gdbserver that is running 
                on the remote target by using the following command form:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ target remote remote-target-ip-address:2345
                </literallayout>
                The <filename>remote-target-ip-address</filename> is the IP address of the
                remote target where the Gdbserver is running. 
                Port 2345 is the port on which the GDBSERVER is running.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdb-using">
            <title>Using the Debugger</title>

            <para>
                You can now proceed with debugging as normal - as if you were debugging
                on the local machine.
                For example, to instruct GDB to break in the "main" function and then 
                continue with execution of the inferior binary use the following commands
                from within GDB:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     (gdb) break main
     (gdb) continue
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                For more information about using GDB, see the project's online documentation at 
                <ulink url="http://sourceware.org/gdb/download/onlinedocs/"/>.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>

<section id="platdev-oprofile">
    <title>Profiling with OProfile</title>

    <para>
        <ulink url="http://oprofile.sourceforge.net/">OProfile</ulink> is a 
        statistical profiler well suited for finding performance 
        bottlenecks in both userspace software and in the kernel. 
        This profiler provides answers to questions like "Which functions does my application spend 
        the most time in when doing X?" 
        Because the Yocto Project is well integrated with OProfile, it makes profiling applications on target 
        hardware straightforward.
    </para>

    <para>
        To use OProfile, you need an image that has OProfile installed. 
        The easiest way to do this is with <filename>tools-profile</filename> in the
        <filename><link linkend='var-IMAGE_FEATURES'>IMAGE_FEATURES</link></filename> variable. 
        You also need debugging symbols to be available on the system where the analysis 
        takes place. 
        You can gain access to the symbols by using <filename>dbg-pkgs</filename> in the
        <filename>IMAGE_FEATURES</filename> variable or by
        installing the appropriate <filename>-dbg</filename> packages. 
    </para>

    <para>
        For successful call graph analysis, the binaries must preserve the frame 
        pointer register and should also be compiled with the 
        <filename>-fno-omit-framepointer</filename> flag. 
        In the Yocto Project you can achieve this by setting the 
        <filename><link linkend='var-SELECTED_OPTIMIZATION'>SELECTED_OPTIMIZATION
        </link></filename> variable to 
        <filename>-fexpensive-optimizations -fno-omit-framepointer -frename-registers -O2</filename>. 
        You can also achieve it by setting the
        <filename><link linkend='var-DEBUG_BUILD'>DEBUG_BUILD</link></filename> variable to "1" in 
        the <filename>local.conf</filename> configuration file.
        If you use the <filename>DEBUG_BUILD</filename> variable you will also add extra debug information 
        that can make the debug packages large.
    </para>

    <section id="platdev-oprofile-target">
        <title>Profiling on the Target</title>

        <para>
            Using OProfile you can perform all the profiling work on the target device. 
            A simple OProfile session might look like the following:
        </para>

        <para>
            <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     # opcontrol --reset
     # opcontrol --start --separate=lib --no-vmlinux -c 5
              .
              .
        [do whatever is being profiled]
              .
              .
     # opcontrol --stop
     $ opreport -cl
            </literallayout>
        </para>

        <para>
            In this example, the <filename>reset</filename> command clears any previously profiled data.
            The next command starts OProfile.
            The options used when starting the profiler separate dynamic library data 
            within applications, disable kernel profiling, and enable callgraphing up to
            five levels deep.
            <note>
                To profile the kernel, you would specify the 
                <filename>--vmlinux=/path/to/vmlinux</filename> option.
                The <filename>vmlinux</filename> file is usually in the Yocto Project file's 
                <filename>/boot/</filename> directory and must match the running kernel.
            </note>
        </para>

        <para> 
            After you perform your profiling tasks, the next command stops the profiler. 
            After that, you can view results with the <filename>opreport</filename> command with options
            to see the separate library symbols and callgraph information.
        </para>

        <para>
            Callgraphing logs information about time spent in functions and about a function's
            calling function (parent) and called functions (children).
            The higher the callgraphing depth, the more accurate the results.  
            However, higher depths also increase the logging overhead.
            Consequently, you should take care when setting the callgraphing depth. 
            <note>
                On ARM, binaries need to have the frame pointer enabled for callgraphing to work.
                To accomplish this use the <filename>-fno-omit-framepointer</filename> option 
                with <filename>gcc</filename>.
            </note>
        </para>

        <para>
            For more information on using OProfile, see the OProfile 
            online documentation at 
            <ulink url="http://oprofile.sourceforge.net/docs/"/>.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="platdev-oprofile-oprofileui">
        <title>Using OProfileUI</title>

        <para>
            A graphical user interface for OProfile is also available. 
            You can download and build this interface from the Yocto Project at
            <ulink url="http://git.yoctoproject.org/cgit.cgi/oprofileui/"></ulink>. 
            If the "tools-profile" image feature is selected, all necessary binaries
            are installed onto the target device for OProfileUI interaction.
        </para>

        <para>
            Even though the Yocto Project usually includes all needed patches on the target device, you 
            might find you need other OProfile patches for recent OProfileUI features.
            If so, see the <ulink url='http://git.yoctoproject.org/cgit.cgi/oprofileui/tree/README'>
            OProfileUI README</ulink> for the most recent information.
        </para>

        <section id="platdev-oprofile-oprofileui-online">
            <title>Online Mode</title>

            <para>
                Using OProfile in online mode assumes a working network connection with the target 
                hardware. 
                With this connection, you just need to run "oprofile-server" on the device. 
                By default, OProfile listens on port 4224. 
                <note>
                    You can change the port using the <filename>--port</filename> command-line 
                    option.
                </note>
            </para>

            <para>
                The client program is called <filename>oprofile-viewer</filename> and its UI is relatively 
                straightforward.
                You access key functionality through the buttons on the toolbar, which
                are duplicated in the menus.
                Here are the buttons:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Connect:</emphasis> Connects to the remote host.
                        You can also supply the IP address or hostname.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Disconnect:</emphasis> Disconnects from the target.
                        </para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Start:</emphasis> Starts profiling on the device.
                        </para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Stop:</emphasis> Stops profiling on the device and 
                        downloads the data to the local host. 
                        Stopping the profiler generates the profile and displays it in the viewer.
                        </para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Download:</emphasis> Downloads the data from the 
                        target and generates the profile, which appears in the viewer.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Reset:</emphasis> Resets the sample data on the device. 
                        Resetting the data removes sample information collected from previous
                        sampling runs. 
                        Be sure you reset the data if you do not want to include old sample information.
                        </para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Save:</emphasis> Saves the data downloaded from the
                        target to another directory for later examination.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><emphasis>Open:</emphasis> Loads previously saved data.
                        </para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                The client downloads the complete 'profile archive' from
                the target to the host for processing. 
                This archive is a directory that contains the sample data, the object files, 
                and the debug information for the object files. 
                The archive is then converted using the <filename>oparchconv</filename> script, which is 
                included in this distribution.
                The script uses <filename>opimport</filename> to convert the archive from
                the target to something that can be processed on the host.
            </para>

            <para>
                Downloaded archives reside in the Yocto Project's build directory in 
                <filename>/tmp</filename> and are cleared up when they are no longer in use.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you wish to perform kernel profiling, you need to be sure 
                a <filename>vmlinux</filename> file that matches the running kernel is available. 
                In the Yocto Project, that file is usually located in 
                <filename>/boot/vmlinux-KERNELVERSION</filename>, where 
                <filename>KERNEL-version</filename> is the version of the kernel. 
                The Yocto Project generates separate <filename>vmlinux</filename> packages for each kernel
                it builds.
                Thus, it should just be a question of making sure a matching package is 
                installed (e.g. <filename>opkg install kernel-vmlinux</filename>. 
                The files are automatically installed into development and profiling images 
                alongside OProfile. 
                A configuration option exists within the OProfileUI settings page that you can use to 
                enter the location of the <filename>vmlinux</filename> file. 
            </para>

            <para>
                Waiting for debug symbols to transfer from the device can be slow, and it
                is not always necessary to actually have them on the device for OProfile use. 
                All that is needed is a copy of the filesystem with the debug symbols present 
                on the viewer system. 
                The <link linkend='platdev-gdb-remotedebug-launch-gdb'>Launching GDB
                on the Host Computer</link> section covers how to create such a directory with 
                the Yocto Project and how to use the OProfileUI Settings dialog to specify the location.
                If you specify the directory, it will be used when the file checksums 
                match those on the system you are profiling.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id="platdev-oprofile-oprofileui-offline">
            <title>Offline Mode</title>

            <para>
                If network access to the target is unavailable, you can generate
                an archive for processing in <filename>oprofile-viewer</filename> as follows:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     # opcontrol --reset
     # opcontrol --start --separate=lib --no-vmlinux -c 5
            .
            .
     [do whatever is being profiled]
            .
            .
     # opcontrol --stop
     # oparchive -o my_archive
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <para>
                In the above example, <filename>my_archive</filename> is the name of the 
                archive directory where you would like the profile archive to be kept. 
                After the directory is created, you can copy it to another host and load it
                using <filename>oprofile-viewer</filename> open functionality.
                If necessary, the archive is converted.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>



</chapter> 
<!-- 
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4 
-->
