<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id='intro'>
<title>Introduction</title>

<section id='intro-welcome'>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
        This manual provides reference information for the current release of the Yocto Project.
        The Yocto Project is an open-source collaboration project focused on embedded Linux
        developers.
        Amongst other things, the Yocto Project uses the Poky build tool to 
        construct complete Linux images.
        You can find complete introductory and getting started information on the Yocto Project
        by reading the 
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html'>   
        Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink>.
        You can also find lots of information on the Yocto Project on the 
        <ulink url="http://www.yoctoproject.org">Yocto Project website</ulink>.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='intro-manualoverview'>
    <title>Documentation Overview</title>
    <para>
        This reference manual consists of the following:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='usingpoky'>Using the Yocto Project</link>:</emphasis> This chapter
                provides an overview of the components that make up the Yocto Project 
                followed by information about debugging images created in the Yocto Project.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='extendpoky'>Extending the Yocto Project</link>:</emphasis> This chapter
                provides information about how to extend and customize the Yocto Project 
                along with advice on how to manage these changes.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='bsp'>Board Support Packages (BSP) - Developer's Guide</link>:</emphasis> 
                This chapter describes the example filesystem layout for BSP development and 
                the click-through licensing scheme.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='platdev'>Platform Development With the Yocto Project</link>:</emphasis> 
                This chapter describes application development, debugging, and profiling using 
                the Yocto Project.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-structure'>Reference: Directory Structure</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix describes the directory structure of the Yocto Project files.
                The Yocto Project files represent the file structure or Git repository created 
                as a result of setting up the Yocto Project on your host development system.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-bitbake'>Reference: BitBake</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix provides an overview of the BitBake tool and its role within 
                the Yocto Project.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-classes'>Reference: Classes</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix describes the classes used in the Yocto Project.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-images'>Reference: Images</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix describes the standard images that the Yocto Project supports.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-features'>Reference: Features</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix describes mechanisms for creating distribution, machine, and image 
                features during the build process using the Yocto Project.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-variables-glos'>Reference: Variables Glossary</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix presents most Yocto Project variables.
                Entries describe the function of the variable and how to apply them.
                </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='ref-varlocality'>Reference: Variable Context</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix provides variable locality or context.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='faq'>Reference: FAQ</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix provides answers for commonly asked questions in the Yocto Project
                development environment.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>
                <link linkend='resources'>Reference: Contributing to the Yocto Project</link>:</emphasis> 
                This appendix provides guidance on how you can contribute back to the Yocto 
                Project.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>


<section id='intro-requirements'>
<title>System Requirements</title>
    <para>
        For system Yocto Project system requirements, see the 
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html#resources'>
        What You Need and How You Get It</ulink> section in the 
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html'>
        Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink>.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='intro-getit'>
    <title>Obtaining the Yocto Project</title>
    <para>
        The Yocto Project development team makes the Yocto Project available through a number 
        of methods:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Releases:</emphasis> Stable, tested releases are available through 
                <ulink url='http://yoctoproject.org/downloads/poky/'/>.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Nightly Builds:</emphasis> These releases are available at
                <ulink url='http://autobuilder.yoctoproject.org/'/>.  
                These builds include Yocto Project releases, meta-toolchain tarballs, and 
                experimental builds.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Yocto Project Website:</emphasis> You can find releases
                of the Yocto Project and supported BSPs at the
                <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org'>Yocto Project website</ulink>.
                Along with these downloads, you can find lots of other information at this site.  
                </para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>

<section id='intro-getit-dev'>
    <title>Development Checkouts</title>
    <para>
        Development using the Yocto Project requires a local copy of the Yocto Project files. 
        You can get these files by downloading a Yocto Project release tarball and unpacking it,  
        or by establishing a Git repository of the files.
        For information on both these methods, see
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/dev-manual/dev-manual.html#getting-setup'>
        Getting Setup</ulink> section in  
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/dev-manual/dev-manual.html'>
        The Yocto Project Development Manual</ulink>.
    </para>
</section>

</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
