<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id='adt-prepare'>

<title>Preparing to Use the Application Development Toolkit (ADT)</title>

<para>
    In order to use the ADT, you must install it, <filename>source</filename> a script to set up the 
    environment, and be sure both the kernel and filesystem image specific to the target architecture 
    exist. 
    This chapter describes how to be sure you meet the ADT requirements.
</para>

<section id='installing-the-adt'>
    <title>Installing the ADT</title>

    <para>
        The following list describes how you can install the ADT, which includes the cross-toolchain.
        Regardless of the installation you choose, you must <filename>source</filename> the cross-toolchain
        environment setup script before you use the toolchain.
        See the "<link linkend='setting-up-the-environment'>Setting Up the Environment</link>"
        section for more information.
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Use the ADT Installer Script:</emphasis>
                This method is the recommended way to install the ADT because it
                automates much of the process for you.
                For example, you can configure the installation to install the QEMU emulator
                and the user-space NFS, specify which root filesystem profiles to download, 
                and define the target sysroot location.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Use an Existing Toolchain Tarball:</emphasis>
                Using this method, you select and download an architecture-specific
                toolchain tarball and then hand-install the toolchain.
                If you use this method, you just get the cross-toolchain and QEMU - you do not 
                get any of the other mentioned benefits had you run the ADT Installer script.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Use the Toolchain from within a Yocto Project Build Tree:</emphasis>
                If you already have a Yocto Project build tree, you can install the cross-toolchain 
                using that tree.
                However, like the previous method mentioned, you only get the cross-toolchain and QEMU - you 
                do not get any of the other benefits without taking separate steps.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <section id='using-the-adt-installer'>
        <title>Using the ADT Installer</title>

        <para>
            To run the ADT Installer, you need to first get the ADT Installer tarball and then run the ADT
            Installer Script.
        </para>

        <section id='getting-the-adt-installer-tarball'>
            <title>Getting the ADT Installer Tarball</title>

            <para>
                The ADT Installer is contained in the ADT Installer tarball.
                You can download the tarball into any directory from  
                <ulink url='http://autobuilder.yoctoproject.org/downloads/yocto-1.1/adt-installer/'></ulink>.
                Or, you can use BitBake to generate the tarball inside the existing Yocto Project 
                build tree.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you use BitBake to generate the ADT Installer tarball, you must 
                <filename>source</filename> the Yocto Project environment setup script located 
                in the Yocto Project file structure before running the <filename>bitbake</filename>
                command that creates the tarball.
            </para>

            <para>
                The following example commands download the Yocto Project release tarball, set up the Yocto 
                Project files structure, set up the environment while also creating the 
                default Yocto Project build tree, 
                and run the <filename>bitbake</filename> command that results in the tarball 
                <filename>~/yocto-project/build/tmp/deploy/sdk/adt_installer.tar.bz2</filename>:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ cd ~
     $ mkdir yocto-project
     $ cd yocto-project
     $ wget http://www.yoctoproject.org/downloads/poky/poky-edison-6.0.tar.bz2
     $ tar xjf poky-edison-6.0.tar.bz2
     $ source poky-edison-6.0/oe-init-build-env
     $ bitbake adt-installer
                </literallayout>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='configuring-and-running-the-adt-installer-script'>
            <title>Configuring and Running the ADT Installer Script</title>

            <para>
                Before running the ADT Installer script, you need to unpack the tarball.
                You can unpack the tarball in any directory you wish.
                Unpacking it creates the directory <filename>adt-installer</filename>, 
                which contains the ADT Installer script (<filename>adt_installer</filename>)
                and its configuration file (<filename>adt_installer.conf</filename>).
            </para>

            <para>
                Before you run the script, however, you should examine the ADT Installer configuration 
                file and be sure you are going to get what you want.  
                Your configurations determine which kernel and filesystem image are downloaded.
            </para>

            <para>  
                The following list describes the configurations you can define for the ADT Installer.  
                For configuration values and restrictions, see the comments in  
                the <filename>adt-installer.conf</filename> file:

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_REPO</filename>: This area 
                        includes the IPKG-based packages and the root filesystem upon which 
                        the installation is based.  
                        If you want to set up your own IPKG repository pointed to by 
                        <filename>YOCTOADT_REPO</filename>, you need to be sure that the 
                        directory structure follows the same layout as the reference directory 
                        set up at <ulink url='http://adtrepo.yoctoproject.org'></ulink>.  
                        Also, your repository needs to be accessible through HTTP.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_TARGETS</filename>: The machine 
                        target architectures for which you want to set up cross-development 
                        environments.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_QEMU</filename>: Indicates whether 
                        or not to install the emulator QEMU.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_NFS_UTIL</filename>: Indicates whether 
                        or not to install user-mode NFS.  
                        If you plan to use the Yocto Eclipse IDE plug-in against QEMU, 
                        you should install NFS.
                        <note>To boot QEMU images using our userspace NFS server, you need 
                            to be running <filename>portmap</filename> or <filename>rpcbind</filename>. 
                            If you are running <filename>rpcbind</filename>, you will also need to add the 
                            <filename>-i</filename> option when <filename>rpcbind</filename> starts up. 
                            Please make sure you understand the security implications of doing this. 
                            You might also have to modify your firewall settings to allow 
                            NFS booting to work.</note></para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_ROOTFS_&lt;arch&gt;</filename>: The root 
                        filesystem images you want to download from the 
                        <filename>YOCTOADT_IPKG_REPO</filename> repository.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_TARGET_SYSROOT_IMAGE_&lt;arch&gt;</filename>: The 
                        particular root filesystem used to extract and create the target sysroot.
                        The value of this variable must have been specified with 
                        <filename>YOCTOADT_ROOTFS_&lt;arch&gt;</filename>.
                        For example, if you downloaded both <filename>minimal</filename> and 
                        <filename>sato-sdk</filename> images by setting 
                        <filename>YOCTOADT_ROOTFS_&lt;arch&gt;</filename>
                        to "minimal sato-sdk", then <filename>YOCTOADT_ROOTFS_&lt;arch&gt;</filename>
                        must be set to either <filename>minimal</filename> or 
                        <filename>sato-sdk</filename>.</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para><filename>YOCTOADT_TARGET_SYSROOT_LOC_&lt;arch&gt;</filename>: The 
                        location on the development host where the target sysroot is created.
                        </para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                After you have configured the <filename>adt_installer.conf</filename> file, 
                run the installer using the following command:
                <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ adt_installer
                </literallayout>
            </para>

            <note>
                The ADT Installer requires the <filename>libtool</filename> package to complete.  
                If you install the recommended packages as described in the 
                "<ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html#packages'>Packages</ulink>"
                section of 
                <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html'>
                The Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink>, then you will have libtool installed.
            </note>

            <para>
                Once the installer begins to run, you are asked whether you want to run in 
                interactive or silent mode.  
                If you want to closely monitor the installation, choose “I” for interactive 
                mode rather than “S” for silent mode.  
                Follow the prompts from the script to complete the installation.
            </para>

            <para>
                Once the installation completes, the ADT, which includes the cross-toolchain, is installed.
                You will notice environment setup files for the cross-toolchain in 
                <filename>/opt/poky/$SDKVERSION</filename>,
                and image tarballs in the <filename>adt-installer</filename>
                directory according to your installer configurations, and the target sysroot located
                according to the <filename>YOCTOADT_TARGET_SYSROOT_LOC_&lt;arch&gt;</filename> variable
                also in your configuration file.
            </para>
         </section>
    </section>

    <section id='using-an-existing-toolchain-tarball'>
        <title>Using a Cross-Toolchain Tarball</title>

        <para>
            If you want to simply install the cross-toolchain by hand, you can do so by using an existing 
            cross-toolchain tarball.  
            If you install the cross-toolchain by hand, you will have to set up the target sysroot separately.
        </para>

        <para>
            Follow these steps:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>Go to  
                    <ulink url='http://autobuilder.yoctoproject.org/downloads/yocto-1.1/toolchain'></ulink> 
                    and find the folder that matches your host development system 
                    (i.e. <filename>i586</filename> for 32-bit machines or 
                    <filename>x86_64</filename> for 64-bit machines).</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Go into that folder and download the toolchain tarball whose name 
                    includes the appropriate target architecture.
                    For example, if your host development system is an Intel-based 64-bit system and 
                    you are going to use your cross-toolchain for an ARM-based target, go into the 
                    <filename>x86_64</filename> folder and download the following tarball:
                    <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     yocto-eglibc-x86_64-i586-toolchain-gmae-1.1.tar.bz2
                   </literallayout>
                    <note>As an alternative to steps one and two, you can build the toolchain tarball 
                        if you have a Yocto Project build tree.
                        Use the <filename>bitbake meta-toolchain</filename> command after you have 
                        sourced the <filename>oe-build-init script</filename> located in the Yocto 
                        Project files.  
                        When the <filename>bitbake</filename> command completes, the toolchain tarball will 
                        be in <filename>tmp/deploy/sdk</filename> in the Yocto Project build tree.
                        </note></para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Make sure you are in the root directory with root privileges and then expand 
                    the tarball.  
                    The tarball expands into <filename>/opt/poky/$SDKVERSION</filename>.
                    Once the tarball in unpacked, the cross-toolchain is installed.
                    You will notice environment setup files for the cross-toolchain in the directory.
                    </para></listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            After installing the toolchain, you must locate the target sysroot tarball and unpack it
            into a location of your choice.
        </para>  
    </section>

    <section id='using-the-toolchain-from-within-the-build-tree'>
        <title>Using BitBake and the Yocto Project Build Tree</title>

        <para>
            A final way of installing just the cross-toolchain is to use BitBake within an existing 
            Yocto Project build tree.
            Follow these steps:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem><para>Source the environment setup script located in the Yocto Project
                    files.
                    The script has the string <filename>init-build-env</filename>
                    as part of the name.</para></listitem> 
                <listitem><para>At this point, you should be sure that the 
                    <filename>MACHINE</filename> variable 
                    in the <filename>local.conf</filename> file found in the Yocto Project 
                    file structure's <filename>conf</filename> directory 
                    is set for the target architecture.
                    Comments within the <filename>local.conf</filename> file list the values you 
                    can use for the <filename>MACHINE</filename> variable.  
                    <note>You can populate the build tree with the cross-toolchains for more 
                        than a single architecture.  
                        You just need to edit the <filename>MACHINE</filename> variable in the 
                        <filename>local.conf</filename> file and re-run the BitBake 
                        command.</note></para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Run <filename>bitbake meta-ide-support</filename> to complete the 
                    cross-toolchain installation.
                    <note>If you change your working directory after you 
                        <filename>source</filename> the environment setup script and before you run
                        the BitBake command, the command will not work. 
                        Be sure to run the <filename>bitbake</filename> command immediately 
                        after checking or editing the <filename>local.conf</filename> but without 
                        changing your working directory.</note>
                    Once BitBake finishes, the cross-toolchain is installed.
                    You will notice environment setup files for the cross-toolchain in the 
                    Yocto Project build tree in the <filename>tmp</filename> directory.
                    Setup script filenames contain the strings <filename>environment-setup</filename>.
                    </para></listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>

        <para>
            After installing the toolchain, you must locate the target sysroot tarball and unpack
            it in a directory of your choice.  
        </para>

        <para>
            WRITER'S NOTE:  Right now I am a little fuzzy on just how you do this.  
            I am not sure if you just grab what is in <filename>build/tmp/deploy/images</filename>
            and then unpack it with the <filename>tar -xjvf [tarball] [directory]</filename> or 
            if you have to run the tarball environment setup script found in 
            <filename>build/tmp</filename> and then run the 
            <filename>runqemu-extract-sdk [tarball] [directory]</filename> command.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>

<section id='setting-up-the-environment'>
    <title>Setting Up the Environment</title>

    <para>
        Before you can use the cross-toolchain, you need to set up the toolchain environment by 
        sourcing the environment setup script.  
        If you used the ADT Installer or used an existing ADT tarball to install the ADT,
        then you can find this script in the <filename>/opt/poky/$SDKVERSION</filename>
        directory.  
        If you used BitBake and the Yocto Project Build Tree to install the cross-toolchain,
        then you can find the environment setup scripts in in the Yocto Project build tree 
        in the <filename>tmp</filename> directory.
    </para>

    <para> 
        Be sure to run the environment setup script that matches the architecture for 
        which you are developing.  
        Environment setup scripts begin with the string “<filename>environment-setup</filename>”
        and include as part of their name the architecture.  
        For example, the environment setup script for a 64-bit IA-based architecture would 
        be the following: 
        <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     /opt/poky/1.1/environment-setup-x86_64-poky-linux
        </literallayout>
    </para>
</section>

<section id='kernels-and-filesystem-images'>
    <title>Kernels and Filesystem Images</title>

    <para>
        You will need to have a kernel and filesystem image to boot using your 
        hardware or the QEMU emulator.  
        That means you either have to build them or know where to get them.
        You can find a quick example of how to build an image in the 
        "<ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html#building-image'>Building an Image</ulink>" section of   
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/yocto-project-qs/yocto-project-qs.html'>
        The Yocto Project Quick Start</ulink>.
        <note><para> 
            The Yocto Project provides basic kernels and filesystem images for several 
            architectures (<filename>x86</filename>, <filename>x86-64</filename>, 
            <filename>mips</filename>, <filename>powerpc</filename>, and <filename>arm</filename>) 
            that you can use unaltered in the QEMU emulator.  
            These kernels and filesystem images reside in the Yocto Project release 
            area - <ulink url='http://autobuilder.yoctoproject.org/downloads/yocto-1.1/machines/'></ulink>
            and are ideal for experimentation within Yocto Project.</para>
            <para>If you plan on remotely deploying and debugging your application from within the 
            Eclipse IDE, you must have an image that supports Sato.
            For information on the image types you can build using the Yocto Project, see
            <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/poky-ref-manual/poky-ref-manual.html#ref-images'>
            Reference: Images</ulink> in  
            <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org/docs/1.1/poky-ref-manual/poky-ref-manual.html'>
            The Yocto Project Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>
        </note>
    </para>

    <para>
        WRITER'S NOTE:  It seems to me that you need to take steps to unpack the image filesystem
        at this point.  
        This would involve running the tarball environment setup script found in 
        <filename>build/tmp</filename> and then running the 
        <filename>runqemu-extract-sdk [tarball] [directory]</filename> command.
    </para>
</section>

</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
